Guide to the Lessons of the Sixties: A history of local Washington, DC activism for peace and justice from 1960-1975:Personal papers, 1937-2016, bulk 1967-1981 MS2392
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Lessons of the Sixties: A history of local Washington, DC activism for peace and justice from 1960-1975: Personal papers
1937-2016
1967-1981
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
MS2392
8 Linear Feet
Lessons of the Sixties is an organization dedicated to documenting the efforts and lessons learned by local DC Metropolitan Area activists, students, organizers and those who dreamed of building a better world through new ideas, political advocacy, local organization building, and other means in the years 1960-1975. Since 2010, the Institute for Policy Studies has served as the organizational home for the Lessons of the 60s providing office space and infrastructural support. Since 2010 the project volunteers have interviewed more than 80 local activists, students, organizers and those who dreamed of building a better world through new ideas, political advocacy, local organization building, and various other means in the Washington, D.C. area in the years 1960-1975. At times during the interviews the interviewees would use personal records as examples or memory prompts. Those records were also donated to GW Special Collections and comprise a more encompassing collection of records of this time period in Washington D.C.'s history. Lessons of the Sixties is an organization dedicated to documenting the efforts and lessons learned by local DC Metropolitan Area activists, students, organizers and those who dreamed of building a better world through new ideas, political advocacy, local organization building, and other means in the years 1960-1975. This collection contains paper records donated by participants in the Lessons of the Sixties oral history project. These paper records including newspaper articles, correspondence, newsletters, pamphlets, images, and buttons. These documents cover many topics including school reform, reprodutive rights, labor issues, anti-vietnam war and government worker rights. These records cover 1937-2016 with the bulk of the records covering 1967-1981.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Arrangement
Organized into 14 series: Dale Brown papers, Irene Elkin papers, Jan Fenty buttons, Madeleine Golde papers, John Hanrahan papers, Norman Oslik papers, Natasha Reatig papers, Irv Riskin papers, Fred Solowey papers, Roberta Spalter-Roth papers, Marcia Sprinkle-Kopit papers, Alice Wolfson papers, Malcolm Davis papers and Larry Aaronson draft of memoir.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Lessons of the Sixties, 2019 November 21 (2019.101)
All these paper records were given to the donor by participants of the oral history project and become the property of the donor to deposit at GW.
Historical
Lessons of the Sixties is an organization dedicated to documenting the efforts and lessons learned by local DC Metropolitan Area activists, students, organizers and those who dreamed of building a better world through new ideas, political advocacy, local organization building, and other means in the years 1960-1975. The organization's goal is to make materials easily available for future activists, historians, students, writers, and media producers. Members have given presentations on their findings in order to facilitate direct dialogue between generations of social justice activists. One of the most significant contributions are the oral histories it conducted between 2010-2019 with local activists. Lessons of the 60s has the objective of focusing on key local and national movements and events of this period in which D.C-area-based residents were involved. These topics include, but are not limited to, 1963 March on Washington, anti-Vietnam War organizing, Black power movement, civil rights movement, DC statehood movement, early battles against gentrification, fair housing, international solidarity, May Day 1971, peace movement, Stop the North Central Freeway/3 Sisters Bridge, student activism for peace and civil rights, and the Women's movement.
Since 2010 the Institute for Policy Studies has served as the organizational home for the Lessons of the 60s providing office space and infrastructural support
Scope and Contents
This collection contains paper records donated by participants in the Lessons of the Sixties oral history project. These paper records including newspaper articles, correspondence, newsletters, pamphlets, images, and buttons. These documents cover many topics including school reform, reprodutive rights, labor issues, anti-vietnam war and government worker rights. Each series is the donation of a separate interviewee. The donors provided keywords for specific folders that have been included as notes for those specific folders. These records cover 1937-2016 with the bulk of the records covering 1967-1981.
Related Materials
Lessons of the Sixties donated materials that are found in several GW collections. The links to the related collection's finding aids are below. Lessons of the Sixties: A history of local Washington, DC activism for peace and justice from 1960-1975: James G. Stockard papers finding aid Lessons of the Sixties: A history of local Washington, DC activism for peace and justice from 1963-1990: Joann Malone papers finding aid Lessons of the Sixties: A history of local Washington, DC activism for peace and justice from 1960-1975: Oral history interviews finding aid To go directly to the assistance provided by the Lessons of the 60s from their website: To watch all the video interviews conducted by the Lessons of the Sixties project, go to the Lessons of the Sixties conducted interviews page If your focus is word searching interviews and document collections use Lessons of the Sixties keyword lists.
Existence and Location of Copies
This donation came with pdf copies of the Advocate. The digital copies are not online due to copyright and accessibility issues. If you would like to use a digital copy please contact Special Collections.
Vietnam War, 1961-1975 -- Protest movements -- United States; Protest movements; Women's rights; Labor Unions -- Washington Metropolitan Area -- History -- 20th Century; Statehood (American politics) -- Washington (D.C.)
- Dale Brown papers, 1970; Series 1
  Biographical / Historical
  High school activist who was arrested distributing anti-Vietnam War material at a military base. Also headed up a students' committee against the war in 1971 for May Day, an attempted shut-down of the US government by the peace movement.
  Biography provided by the donor.
  Scope and Contents
  This series includes documents from Dale Brown's high school student activism against the Vietnam War, focused around 1971.
  oral history
  Dale Brown was a participant in the Lessons of the Sixties oral history project. The interview is part of collection MS2388. Listen to the interview..
  - High School Antiwar, 1970; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    General
    Keywords provided by the donor: Washington Student Mobilization Committee, Vietnam War, High School activism, Student Bill of Rights, Free speech
- Irene Elkin papers, 1967-2014; 1967-1973; Series 2
  Irene Elkin has been an activist from the 1950s through the 2010s. During the 1960s and early 1970s, she was chair of the Schools Committee of the Adams-Morgan Community Council, fighting successfully for community control of Morgan School (now the Marie Reed Community Learning Center). As a government employee, Elkin was active in the Vietnam Moratorium Committee at NIH/NIMH (VNMC) and Federal Employees for Peace. On the Moratorium Committee, she served as one of the coordinators of the group and was one of the plaintiffs in a case brought against the Secretary of Health, Education, and Welfare for use of the NIH auditorium for speakers invited by the VNMC.
  This series includes materials from Irene Elkin's participation in the successful efforts during the 1960s and early 1970s to establish community control of Morgan School in the Adams-Morgan neighborhood of Washington, D.C.
  - History of Morgan School, 1967-1968; Series 2 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Keywords provided by the donor: Adams Morgan Community School Project, Paul Lauter – Antioch College, Morgan Community School History Committee, Irene Elkin (Waskow), Edward Jackson
  - Ed Jackson – History of Morgan Community School, 1967; Series 2 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Keywords provided by the donor: Ed (Edward) Jackson, History of Morgan Community School, Community School Proposal, School Staffing, Testimony, Bishop Marie Reed, First Annual Report, Bibliography of Morgan Community School, First Community School Board
  - Press Clippings, 1967-1968; Series 2 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Keywords provided by the donor: CITY-Schools: Morgan's Tentative Revolution, The American Teacher: 'Guerrilla warfare' in the the ghetto, Washington Star: Community Split on Goals of Morgan School Experiment, Washington Daily News, Washington Post
  - Jeanne Walton thesis on Morgan Community School, 1968; Series 2 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Keywords provided by the donor: Jeanne Walton Thesis on Morgan Community School
  - Morgan School Building, 1967-1972; Series 2 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Keywords provided by the donor: Committee on Proposed School Building, Groundbreaking
  - Adams Community School, 1972-1973; Series 2 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Keywords provided by the donor: Flyers, statements, Adams Community School Board Election, Irene Elkin Statement
  - Kenneth Haskins, 1967-1994; Series 2 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Keywords provided by the donor: Kenneth Haskins – Principal Morgan School, Obituary, Morris T. Keeton – Antioch, Jeanne Walton, Dave Darland, Marguerite A. Dickey
  - Interview Notes, 2014; Series 2 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Keywords provided by the donor: Elkin notes for oral interview on Morgan Community School
  - Community Input, 1967-1968; Series 2 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Keywords provided by the donor: Community input for Morgan School, Curriculum Committee, Morgan Community School Newsletter, Morgan School Board Election, Door-to-Door Worker's Report form
  - Morgan Follow Through Application, 1969-1970; Series 2 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Keywords provided by the donor: Morgan School Follow Through Application, Community Teacher Recruitment Program, Workshop in Creative Learning
- Jan Fenty buttons, Circa 1970; Series 3
  Women's activist end of 60s and early 70s; peace movement organizer early 70s, longtime DC resident.
  Biograph provided by the donor.
  This series contains buttons from the 1970s related to women's rights movement.
  Jan Fenty was a participant in the Lessons of the Sixties oral history project. The interview is part of collection MS2388. Listen to the interview..
  - Womens liberation buttons, Circa 1970; Series 3 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Madeleine Golde papers, 1937-1981; 1967-1981; Series 4
  Madeleine Golde came to Washington, DC in 1967 in the era of President Johnson's Great Society programs to try to make a difference in terms of social programs for the poor. During her seven years in HEW, she was an outspoken activist against the war in Vietnam within the federal bureaucracy, including helping to form government-wide anti-war organizations; launched an underground newspaper, The Advocate, that circulated widely throughout the Dept for 5 years, tackling issues ranging from treatment of minorities in HEW, to effectiveness of HEW programs and free speech rights for employees; and played an important role in activating a moribund union local in her Department. For the past 40 years, she has continued to be an active participant in advocating for the rights of workers and the protection of our communities.
  This series contains documents covering Madeleine Golde's activist work during the years 1968-1975, including her leadership of the The Advocate newsletter, her union-related work including HEW Local 41 and the Coalition for Labor Union Women, and her work government-wide organizing through her involvement in Federal Employees Against the War in Vietnam, Federal Employees for a Democratic Society and Federal Employees for Peace. The Advocate was an independent newsletter published by and for Department of Health, Education and Welfare employees in the Washington, D.C. area. It was designed to be a vehicle to examine and critique the programs and policies of the Department as well as larger political issues such as the War in Vietnam. It also included information on activities of interest to HEW employees. It was initially designed as a monthly newsletter. It began in February, 1968 and the last issue appeared in the Spring of 1973. In total, 47 issues were published. It was widely distributed and read throughout HEW in the Washington area and faced multiple legal challenges from the leadership of HEW.
  Madeleine Gold was a participant in the Lessons of the Sixties oral history project. The interview is part of collection MS2388. Listen to the interview..
  - The Advocate – Volume 1, 1968-1969; Series 4 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Keywords provided by the donor: Volume 1 -1968-1969: The Advocate, HEW employee newsletter, underground newspaper, social welfare group, Secretary John Gardner, Thursday Discussion Group, Mary Switzer - Administrator of Social and Rehabilitation Services, Poor People's Campaign, Vietnam peace petition, Secretary Wilbur Cohen, Federal Employees Against the War in Vietnam, Federal Employees for a Democratic Society, HEW summer interns, the Hatch Act, employee conduct regulations, Office of Student and Youth Affairs, lawsuit against Wilbur Cohen, Zona Hostetler, ACLU, Fort Detrick, chemical and biological warfare, Local 41 of AFGE, American Federation of Government Employees, cafeteria boycott, youth programs, Feds Film Forum, welfare system.
    Existence and Location of Copies
    This donation came with pdf copies of the Advocate. The digital copies are not online due to copyright and accessibility issues. If you would like to use a digital copy please contact Special Collections.
  - The Advocate – Volume 2, 1969-1970; Series 4 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Keywords provided by the donor: Volume 2 - 1969-1970: The Advocate, internal security office of HEW, agency relocation, Parklawn Building, President Nixon, Father Berrigan, Christian guerrillas, civil disobedience, inner-city youth, racism in mental health, Federal Employees Against the ABM petition, anti-ballistic missile system, equal employment opportunity, The Condition of the Federal Employee and How to Change It, Charleston hospital workers strike, worker rights, union organizing, Public Information Act, picket and rally at Parklawn, Office of Education, school desegregation, Vietnam Moratorium, Julius Hobson, Civil Service Commission, 1969 March on Washington, Secretary Robert Finch, Family Assistance Plan, welfare reform, NIH/NIMH Vietnam Moratorium Committee, funding for cancer, Michael Tigar, Karl Hess, DRUM monthly newsletter for black government employees, SSA Discussion Group.
  - The Advocate – Volume 3, 1970-1971; Series 4 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Keywords provided by the donor: Volume 3 - 1970-1971: The Advocate, civil rights policy, credit union reform, Nixon's Executive Order on Agency Relocation, convention for federal employees, Committee on the Rights and Responsibilities of Federal Employees, Nixon on desegregation, day care in HEW, 1970 Hatfield-McGovern amendment to cut Vietnam War funding, penal reform, criminal justice reform, housing crisis, HEW employees action for peace and social priorities, Office of Education, EEO (equal employment opportunity) in HEW, HEW Action Project, HEW day care, racism in HEW, arrest of Black HEW employees, upward mobility, HEW Task Force Against Racial Discrimination, non-voting D.C. Congressional delegate, The HEW 52
  - The Advocate – Volume 4, 1971; Series 4 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Keywords provided by the donor: Volume 4 - 1971: The Advocate, Elliott Richardson, Combined Federal Campaign, Rennie Davis, Barry Katz, Civil Service Commission, The People's Lobby, National Welfare Rights Organization, Southern Christian Leadership Conference, Richardson's Wall, The Committee on Upward Mobility, Employee's Action Coalition, AFGE Local 41, The People's Fund, HEW Action Project, Bill of Rights for Federal Employees, Daniel Ellsberg, Federal Code of Conduct, award dinner for Daniel Ellsberg, freedom of speech for employees, Nixonomics, book review: Regulating the Poor, HEW day care.
  - The Advocate – Volumes 5 and 6, 1972-1973; Series 4 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Keywords provided by the donor: Volume 5 - 1972: The Advocate, proposed HEW incinerator, the "Castro" speech, health insurance for federal employees, Office of Civil Rights, lobotomies, secret air war in Laos, HEW Bond Drive, the Golden List of non-subscribers, AFGE Local 41, lettuce boycott, Know your Rights on leafletting, upward mobility, the Hatch Act, the politics of racism, HEW central payroll employees; Volume 6 - 1973: U.S. prohibits The Advocate distribution.
  - The Advocate – press coverage, Circa 1970-1971; Series 4 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - The Advocate – correspondence and anti-war, 1971-1973; Series 4 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - HEW [Health, Education and Welfare] Thursday Discussion Group, 1967-1968; Series 4 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - 1968 Federal Employees Against the War petition, 1967; Series 4 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - [Federal Employees for a a Democratic Society] FEDS Articles of Incorporation, 1969; Series 4 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - [Federal Employees for a a Democratic Society] FEDS official, 1970; Series 4 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - [Federal Employees for a a Democratic Society] FEDS Film Forum, Circa 1970; Series 4 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - [Federal Employees for a a Democratic Society] FEDS Antiwar actions, 1969-1970; Series 4 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - HEW [Health, Education and Welfare] Anti-Vietnam Actions, 1971-1972; Series 4 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - HEW [Health, Education and Welfare] Social Welfare Group – 1968, Series 4 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - The Condition of the Federal Employee and How to Change It, 1969; Series 4 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Federal Employees Convention 1970, Series 4 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - ACLU Cases/May Day, 1937-1981; Series 4 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Federal Employees for Peace, 1969-1972; Series 4 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - [Federal Employees for a a Democratic Society] FEDS Daniels Ellsberg Testimonial Dinner – 1971, Series 4 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - HEW [Health, Education and Welfare] Meetings with Richardson and HEW 52 – 1971, Series 4 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Agency Newsletters, 1971-1972; Series 4 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - News Clippings – Spring Offensive - 1971, Series 4 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - HEW AP [ [Health, Education and Welfare Action Project] [Health, Education and Welfare] AP, 1970-1971; Series 4 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Poor Peoples Campaign – 1968, Series 4 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Resignation of HEW Secretary John Gardner – 1968, Series 4 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Federal Employees – Papers, Circa 1969; Series 4 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Washington Community Lobby, 1972; Series 4 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Anti-Vietnam Actions – 1969-1972, Series 4 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - NIH/NIMH Moratorium Committee, 1969-1971; Series 4 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Federal employee actions, 1969-1973; Series 4 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Federal Employees for a Democratic Society -- banner, Circa 1972; MS2392 Series 4 (Banner 1)
    Immediate Source of Acquisition
    Delivered by Lessons of the Sixties in February 2021. Part of accession 2019.101.
    Information provided by the donor: Federal Employees for A Democratic Society (FEDS) was formed in the Spring of 1968. FEDS grew out of an effort by a number of federal employees from different agencies to circulate a government-wide petition against the war in Vietnam. FEDS was intended to be a more permanent organization of federal employees representing a broad range of federal agencies in the Washington Metropolitan Area. It's mission was to not only address issues of the war but to examine federal programs with the focus of making them more responsive to the needs of the constituents they were intended to serve. The FEDS banner was used in a number of demonstrations and activities that were held over around a two-year period into 1970. During this period FEDS helped organize active agency-based groups, held regular meetings to organize government-wide anti-war activities, carried out a conference designed to look at a number of key social policy issues and employee rights issues, and ran a regular film festival related to important issues of the day.
  - Federal Employees for Peace digital copies of photographs some from publications, MS2392 Series 4
    Custodial History
    The digital images in this folder came to Special Collections in February 2021 from the Lesson of the Sixties.
    The digital files in this donation include the following: 1. Daniel Ellsberg at dinner in his honor, Undated 2. Ellsberg dinner - audience, Undated 3. Ellsburg dinner - declassified stamp, Undated 4. Federal Employees for Peace rally sign (jpg version), Circa 1972 5. Federal Employees for Peace rally sign (pdf version), Circa 1972
    Conditions Governing Access
    These images are only in digital form and are not online. Please seek assistance from staff for access to these images.
    Information provided by the donor: Federal Employees for Peace (FEPS) - FEPS came into being at the end of 1970. FEPS served a coalition bringing together representatives of many federal agency Vietnam Moratorium Committees, American Federation of Government Employee locals, agency discussion groups, and individual federal employees commited to ending the war. It was primarily focused on continuing efforts to organize efforts throughout the government in the Washington DC area to end the war in Vietnam. The organization ceased to be once the war ended in 1975. The banner was used in many anti-war rallies throughout this period. Among its many activities, FEPS also held a very successful dinner in September of 1971 to honor Daniel Ellsberg for releasing the Pentagon Papers, and conducted a referendum on the Vietnam War among Federal employees, with 83% of 7,407 employees from across the government voting to end the war. The banner was again used by current and former federal employees in demonstrations opposing the Iraq War in 2003.
  - Federal Employees for Peace in Lafayette Square -- banner, MS2392 Series 4 (Banner 2)
    The digital files in this donation include the following images of this banner. It appears to be two images each has a pdf and jpg: 1. Federal Employees for Peace banner - (pdf version), 1972 April 24 2. Federal Employees for Peace banner in Lafayette Square - (jpg version), 1972 April 24 3. Federal Employees for Peace banner in Lafayette Square- (pdf version), 1972 April 24 4. Federal Employees for Peace banner in Lafayette Square- (jpg version), 1972 April 24
  - Federal Employees in the News [1/2], Circa 1970; Series 4 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Federal Employees in the News [2/2], Circa 1970; Series 4 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - HEW [Health, Education and Welfare] Task Force Against Racial Discrimination, 1972; Series 4 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Federal Employees Advocacy Center, 1971; Series 4 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Employee Rights, 1969-1971; Series 4 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - AFGE [American Federation of Government Employees ] Local 41, 1969-1972; Series 4 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Local 41 Newsletters [American Federation of Government Employees ], 1970-1974; Series 4 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - AFGE [American Federation of Government Employees ] Local 41 News Clippings, Circa 1973-1974; Series 4 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Local 41 Decentralization [American Federation of Government Employees ], 1974; Series 4 (Box 4, Folder 9)